NICOLAS ARAGON BARRERO

Email: nico.aragonbarrero@gmail.com

Nationality: Spanish Date of birth: 03/01/1989

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/nicolas-aragon-barrero-5920a723/

Github: @nicoarbar

Address: Madrid, Spain - Available for relocation

SUMMARY

I am a Data Engineer with experience in consulting in the end-to-end process of managing analytic systems. From analyzing the business requirements with the clients, to implementing the business model by designing the relational database, extracting, transforming and loading the data into databases, and managing the visualization of the data into reports and dashboards. Always analyzing the quality and the integrity of the data in every step of the process.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Role: Senior Data Engineer Company: Cognizant Location: Madrid, Spain

Period: February 2022 - Present

Responsibilities:

Responsible for the Data Engineering backend of a big retailer company in the world.

Analyzing the data we need to use in order to deliver the data required by the business units. Being in touch with the client everyday to understand what they want to achieve and translating that into code design.

Managing a small team of developers and establishing the standards for coding, testing in the repository. Reviewing architectural decisions with the platform architect. Designing and coding ETL processes. Pair programming with some of the junior developers and mentoring them.

Working in Azure, using Databricks (using the pyspark framework) for ETL, Azure Datalake to store the data, and Azure DataFactory for orchestration and Synapse as a datawarehouse.

Role: Junior Data Engineer **Company:** Indra (Minsait) **Location:** Madrid, Spain

Period: March 2018 - February 2022

Responsibilities:

Analyzing the business requirements of the client to implement a datawarehouse and a datamart to analyze operational data.

Designing and creating the relational database to implement the business model, using traditional databases such as Teradata, or on cloud platform using Amazon Web Services databases such as Athena and Redshift extracting the data from an S3 database.

Designing the ETL process that goes from having the data in flat files from the datalake to the datamart. Using SAP Data Services for traditional ETL processes, and in AWS Glue using Pyspark, Lambda functions and Step Functions.

Designing the relational model for the data visualization and creating reports using Microstrategy Developer.

Attending and solving the possible issues in the data quality and integrity in the data flow from end to end. Improving the performance of AWS Glue Jobs and SQL queries, that make up the ETL process and the reports in the visualization. Presenting the client different reports using data visualization and offering possible solutions based on their needs.

Role: PhD Course

Company: Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

Location: Madrid, Spain

Period: September 2017 - October 2017

Responsibilities:

Initial study of computational models of biological neural networks in order to adapt them to artificial neural networks towards its application to artificial intelligence using Python and R.

Role: Assistant to Ambassador - Internship **Company:** Spanish Ministry of Foreign Affairs

Location: Madrid, Spain

Period: October 2015 - February 2016

Responsibilities:

Assistant to the Spanish Ambassador for the Pacific Alliance office, Rafael Dezcallar de Mazarredo (Currently Spanish Ambassador in China).

Political analysis of the role of Spain in Latin America and the Pacific Alliance, and implementation of its policies and commercial activities.

Organizing staff related issues such as meetings, preparing talking points in the agenda and developing proposals.

Role: Research Intern

Company: Vlaams Instituut voor Biotechnologie of Ghent University

Location: Ghent, Belgium

Period: February 2013 - September 2013

Responsibilities:

Research for my Master Thesis of Biochemistry: *Study of A20 in intestinal inflammation*. Researching the molecular pathways concerning NF-KB as a regulatory factor regarding inflammation, concerning the A20 protein and its regulation in inflammation response in the intestinal tract.

Statistical analysis and experimental design,

EDUCATION

Degree: Master in Big Data and Business Analytics

University: IMF Business School / Universidad Camilo José Cela

Location: Online

Period: November 2018 – November 2020

Degree: Bachelor's in philosophy

University: Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

Location: Madrid, Spain

Period: September 2010 - July 2016

Degree: Bachelor in Biochemistry

University: Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

Location: Madrid, Spain

Period: September 2008 - July 2014

UNIVERSITY SCHOLARSHIPS TO STUDY ABROAD

Scholarship: Convenios Internacionales Scholarship – Bachelor in Philosophy

University: University of Melbourne **Location:** Melbourne, Australia

Period: February 2015 - June 2015

Scholarship: CEAL Scholarship of Banco Santander - Bachelor in Philosophy **University:** Instituto Tecnológico de Estudios Superiores de Monterrey

Location: Mexico City, Mexico

Period: August 2014 - December 2014

Scholarship: Erasmus Scholarship - Bachelor in Biochemistry

University: Ghent University **Location:** Ghent, Belgium

Period: September 2012 - September 2013

TECHNICAL CERTIFICATIONS

- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate

- AWS Certified Developer Associate

- Azure Fundamentals

- Azure AI Fundamentals

- Azure Data Engineer Associate

- Google Cloud Digital Leader

COMPUTATIONAL SKILLS

Data Analysis: SQL, Teradata, SAP Data Services, Microstrategy **Programming Languages:** SQL, Python, Pyspark, R, bash scripting.

Methodologies: CI/CD, Git, Agile Methodology

AWS services: S3, Athena, Redshift, Dynamo, Glue, Lambda, Step Functions, SNS, Secrets Manager, Cloud Watch, Cloud Trail, Sagemaker, Cloud Formation, Code Build, Code Commit,

Code Deploy, Code Pipeline, SAM

Azure Services: Blob Storage, Synapse, Databricks, Data Factory, Key Vault

LANGUAGES

Fluent in Spanish and English.